Subtitle Provide by dramacool.asia Translator [Admin.@YNG]
Legenda cedida pelo tradutor dramacool.asia [Admin.@YNG]
[Footprints of Change]
[Pegadas da Mudança]
[Episode 10]
[Episódio 10]
Hungry?
Esfomeado?
Haven't had dinner?
Não jantou?
I'm not in the mood.
Não estou com disposição.
Guess the talk didn't go well.
Acho que a conversa não foi boa.
Tell me about it.
Conte-me sobre isso.
They really have no idea
Eles realmente não têm ideia
about the Japanese strength and capabilities.
sobre a força e as capacidades japonesas.
Do you think...
Acha...
my dad was really killed by the Japanese?
o meu pai foi realmente morto pelos japoneses?
We've got plenty of men,
Temos muitos homens,
but we're no match for the Japanese.
mas não somos páreo para os japoneses.
Pistols are no match for machine guns.
As pistolas não são páreo para as metralhadoras.
That warlord Zhang in the northeast—
Aquele senhor da guerra Zhang no nordeste—
wasn't he powerful?
ele não era poderoso?
Didn't he still get killed by the Japanese bomb?
Ainda não foi morto pela bomba japonesa?
Now Master just
Agora Mestre apenas
got a new son late in life.
ganhou um novo filho mais tarde na vida.
In his mind, he's still
Na sua mente, ele ainda está
some hot-blooded young guy.
um jovem de sangue quente.
We need to splash some cold water on him
Precisamos de lhe deitar um pouco de água fria
to distract him.
para o distrair.
Once his energy is diverted,
Uma vez que a sua energia é desviada,
he won't have time for the workers' strike.
não terá tempo para a greve dos trabalhadores.
How do we do it?
Como fazemos isso?
No way.
Não é possível.
That's my brother.
Este é o meu irmão.
"Boiling beans on beanstalks—
"Feijões cozidos em pés de feijão—
the beans weep, burned by their own kind."
os feijões choram, queimados pelos seus semelhantes."
I'll take all of these.
Vou levá-los todos.
Wrap them up for me.
Embrulhe-os para mim.
Madam Yanhong.
Senhora Yanhong.
Siyun.
Sião.
Waitress,
Garçonete,
bring me your most expensive necklace.
traga-me o seu colar mais caro.
Who is this?
Quem é?
This is my sister-in-law.
Esta é a minha cunhada.
Madam Yanhong.
Senhora Yanhong.
Bring me another expensive one.
Traga-me outro caro.
Here, Siyun.
Toma, Siyun.
This is for you.
Isto é para si.
The other one is for your sister-in-law.
A outra é para a sua cunhada.
You've helped me a lot
Você ajudou-me muito
with my baby's matters.
com os assuntos do meu bebé.
Thank you, Madam Yanhong.
Obrigada, Senhora Yanhong.
I can't accept this gift.
Não posso aceitar este presente.
I provided medical treatment.
Eu forneci tratamento médico.
Mr. Zeng has already paid the consultation fee.
O Sr. Zeng já pagou a taxa de consulta.
That's not the same.
Não é a mesma coisa.
Even though he's paid you,
Mesmo que ele lhe tenha pago,
this is my gift.
esse é o meu presente.
Please take it.
Por favor, pegue.
It's not that expensive.
Não é assim tão caro.
I really can't.
Eu não posso mesmo.
I will keep
Eu vou manter
your baby in mind.
o seu bebé em mente.
Alright, I won't force you then.
Tudo bem, então não o vou forçar.
Once my baby's born,
Quando o meu bebé nascer,
I'll prepare a proper gift for you.
Vou preparar um presente adequado para si.
You must accept it then.
Deve aceitar isso então.
Siyun,
Sião,
let me tell you,
deixa-me contar,
all those little ailments I had before,
todas aquelas pequenas doenças que eu tinha antes,
they've vanished.
desapareceram.
I guess that's what they call "good news brings good health."
Acho que é a isto que chamam "boas notícias trazem boa saúde".
Congratulations.
Parabéns.
I know what you're thinking.
Eu sei o que está a pensar.
That I only married the old man for money.
Que só casei com o velho por dinheiro.
Or what else?
Ou que mais?
Of course I'm in it for the money.
É claro que estou nisto pelo dinheiro.
Isn't it good to be rich?
Não é bom ser rico?
With money,
Com dinheiro,
I can buy whatever I want.
Posso comprar o que quiser.
My child and I
O meu filho e eu
can live a good life.
pode viver uma vida boa.
That's why
É por isso
a woman
uma mulher
has to be shrewd.
tem de ser astuto.
I didn't have a choice.
Não tive escolha.
So if I had to choose—I'd choose money.
Assim, se tivesse de escolher, escolheria dinheiro.
Siyun,
Sião,
do you think my baby
acha que o meu bebé
will be a boy or a girl?
será um menino ou uma menina?
That I can't tell.
Isso não sei dizer.
Can traditional medicine predict it?
A medicina tradicional pode prever isso?
I don't know.
Não sei.
What if it's a girl—
E se for uma menina—
does that mean less money for me?
isso significa menos dinheiro para mim?
Forget it. I won't think about it.
Esqueça. Não vou pensar nisso.
I'll just burn incense every day
Vou queimar incenso todos os dias
when I get back to pray for a boy.
quando voltar para rezar por um menino.
Alright, I should go now.
Muito bem, preciso de ir agora.
Take good care of yourself, Madam Yanhong.
Cuide-se bem, Senhora Yanhong.
Okay, I won't see you out.
Certo, não te vou acompanhar até à saída.
My belly is getting bigger.
A minha barriga está a crescer.
I need to buy more new clothes.
Preciso de comprar mais roupa nova.
Let's go, Sis.
Vamos mana.
It was this necklace just now, right?
Foi este colar agora há pouco, certo?
Siyun,
Sião,
it's such a nice necklace.
É um colar tão bonito.
Why didn't you accept it?
Por que razão não aceitou?
Taking gifts from others is a burden.
Aceitar presentes dos outros é um fardo.
It doesn't feel easy.
Não parece fácil.
Then here's an idea.
Então aqui vai uma ideia.
Next time you
Da próxima vez você
treat those rich ladies,
tratar aquelas senhoras ricas,
take me with you.
leve-me consigo.
You might feel awkward, but I don't.
Pode sentir-se estranho, mas eu não.
I'll accept them for you.
Eu aceitá-los-ei para você.
Dr. Lin! Dr. Lin!
Doutor Lin! Doutor Lin!
Come with me quickly!
Venha depressa comigo!
Madam Yanhong's not good!
A senhora Yanhong não é boa!
What happened?
O que aconteceu?
Madam Yanhong,
Senhora Yanhong,
what's wrong?
o que está mal?
My belly hurts.
Dói-me a barriga.
I just bled.
Eu apenas sangrei.
Do you think I'll be alright?
Achas que vou ficar bem?
Fu,
Era,
call a car.
chamar um carro.
We're going to the hospital.
Vamos ao hospital.
Okay.
Ok.
Sis, I'll accompany Madam Yanhong to the hospital.
Irmã, acompanharei a senhora Yanhong até ao hospital.
You call the hospital
Você liga para o hospital
and tell them to prepare for surgery.
e diga-lhes para se prepararem para a cirurgia.
Also,
Também,
notify Cheng Ao to come to the hospital.
notificar Cheng Ao para ir para o hospital.
Alright.
Tudo bem.
Relax.
Descontrair.
Give the patient a blood transfusion.
Faça ao doente uma transfusão de sangue.
Call the anesthetist.
Ligue para o anestesista.
Get ready for surgery.
Prepare-se para a cirurgia.
Am I going to die?
Eu vou morrer?
No.
Não.
Don't be nervous.
Não fique nervoso.
Take deep breaths.
Respire fundo.
We'll give you blood.
Nós dar-lhe-emos sangue.
Once the anesthetic's in, it won't hurt.
Depois de a anestesia ser aplicada, não vai doer.
Director,
Diretor,
maybe you should step out.
Talvez devesse sair.
People outside are insisting on seeing you.
As pessoas lá fora estão a insistir em vê-lo.
I'll step out for a moment.
Vou sair por um momento.
I'll be right back to perform your surgery.
Já volto para realizar a sua cirurgia.
Dr. Lin.
Dr. Lin.
Siyun,
Sião,
what's going on?
o que está a acontecer?
When I was at the department store today,
Quando hoje estava na loja de departamentos,
I ran into Madam Yanhong.
Encontrei Madame Yanhong.
She suddenly felt unwell.
De repente, ela sentiu-se mal.
After examination, we found out
Após o exame, descobrimos
she's showing signs of miscarriage.
está a apresentar sinais de aborto espontâneo.
But...
Mas...
she was fine when she left home this morning.
ela estava bem quando saiu de casa esta manhã.
How could this happen?
Como pôde acontecer?
She's still hemorrhaging.
Ela ainda está com hemorragia.
The situation is critical.
A situação é crítica.
What about the baby?
E o bebé?
Answer him!
Responda-lhe!
I'm sorry, Dr. Lin.
Sinto muito, Dr. Lin.
Please go ahead.
Por favor, vá em frente.
We can only save
Só podemos salvar
either the baby or the mother.
tanto o bebé como a mãe.
Yanhong.
Yanhong.
Save the mother.
Salve a mãe.
Wait.
Espera.
Dr. Lin,
Dr. Lin,
save the baby instead.
em vez disso, salve o bebé.
Here's a small gift.
Aqui está um pequeno presente.
Thank you for your help.
Obrigado pela ajuda.
Director, her blood pressure is dropping.
Diretora, a pressão dela está a baixar.
Almost unmeasurable.
Quase incomensurável.
If we force delivery,
Se forçarmos a entrega,
we might not be able to save the mother.
talvez não consigamos salvar a mãe.
[Emergency Room]
[Pronto Socorro]
Is it a boy or girl?
É menino ou menina?
Madam Yanhong's condition
A condição de Madame Yanhong
has stabilized.
estabilizou.
What about the baby?
E o bebé?
The baby...
O bebé...
didn't make it.
não conseguiu.
What did I just tell you?
O que é que eu acabei de te dizer?
I am a doctor.
Sou médico.
I had no choice.
Não tive escolha.
Didn't you say there was a choice?
Não disse que havia escolha?
Father.
Pai.
Get out of the way!
Sai da frente!
Something's wrong here.
Há aqui alguma coisa errada.
We need to investigate first.
Precisamos de investigar primeiro.
Move!
Mover!
Take him away!
Levem-no embora!
Get out of here!
Sai daqui!
Father!
Pai!
Father, I beg you.
Pai, eu te imploro.
Father, don't shoot.
Pai, não dispare.
Father!
Pai!
Father, you can't shoot!
Pai, não pode disparar!
Father, you can't kill her!
Pai, não pode matá-la!
Father!
Pai!
Cheng Ao,
Cheng Ao,
from today on,
a partir de hoje,
your 20-year relationship with our Zeng family
a sua relação de 20 anos com a nossa família Zeng
is over.
acabou.
Are you okay?
Está bem?
I'm fine.
Estou bem.
Yanhong will recover, right?
Yanhong vai recuperar, certo?
She's not even 20 yet.
Ela ainda não tem sequer 20 anos.
Her body should recover quickly.
O corpo dela deve recuperar rapidamente.
She can have children again.
Ela pode voltar a ter filhos.
That's good.
Está bom.
I'm sorry.
Lamento.
What are you sorry for?
Do que se desculpa?
You didn't do anything wrong.
Não fez nada errado.
If it were me,
Se fosse eu,
I would've chosen the same.
Eu teria escolhido o mesmo.
I just find it all so sudden and bewildering.
Acho tudo tão repentino e desconcertante.
Dalun suddenly
Dalun de repente
started working with the Japanese.
começou a trabalhar com os japoneses.
My father
O meu pai
suddenly cut ties with me.
cortou relações comigo de repente.
I used to think
Eu costumava pensar
I could handle many things,
Eu conseguia lidar com muitas coisas,
face all kinds of situations.
face all kinds of situations.
♪ The stars shimmer in the sky ♪
♪ The stars shimmer in the sky ♪
But now I don't know.
But now I don't know.
♪ Like hearts flickering between light and dark ♪
♪ Like hearts flickering between light and dark ♪
♪ Their gentle light brightens the world ♪
♪ Their gentle light brightens the world ♪
I don't know...
I don't know...
I just don't know what to do.
I just don't know what to do.
♪ Waiting for dawn to come again ♪
♪ Waiting for dawn to come again ♪
♪ You and I, caught in troubled times ♪
♪ You and I, caught in troubled times ♪
♪ Tangled in this world ♪
♪ Tangled in this world ♪
When I first returned to China,
When I first returned to China,
♪ If destiny's chains can't be broken ♪
♪ If destiny's chains can't be broken ♪
my dad had just passed.
my dad had just passed.
♪ Then I'll spend my life with you ♪
♪ Then I'll spend my life with you ♪
I've also trusted the wrong people
I've also trusted the wrong people
and been deceived.
and been deceived.
When I wanted to open a hospital,
When I wanted to open a hospital,
♪ What we've loved, what we've said ♪
♪ What we've loved, what we've said ♪
I faced many obstacles too.
I faced many obstacles too.
♪ Won't be swept away by wind or rain ♪
♪ Won't be swept away by wind or rain ♪
I've been weak,
I've been weak,
I've been upset—
I've been upset—
♪ What we've suffered, what we've missed ♪
♪ What we've suffered, what we've missed ♪
but I still made it through step by step.
but I still made it through step by step.
♪ Shapes the loneliness of our parting ♪
♪ Shapes the loneliness of our parting ♪
Besides,
Besides,
back then,
back then,
you were always there supporting me.
you were always there supporting me.
♪ What we've loved, what we've said ♪
♪ What we've loved, what we've said ♪
Now I'm here.
Now I'm here.
♪ The bonds of this life that never fade ♪
♪ The bonds of this life that never fade ♪
I'll always be with you
I'll always be with you
♪ I'll treasure what you gave me ♪
♪ I'll treasure what you gave me ♪
and support you.
and support you.
Don't worry.
Don't worry.
♪ That brightness in the darkness ♪
♪ That brightness in the darkness ♪
Things will get better.
Things will get better.
♪ I'll treasure what you gave me ♪
♪ I'll treasure what you gave me ♪
♪ That brightness in the darkness ♪
♪ That brightness in the darkness ♪
Siyun,
Siyun,
when are you free
when are you free
these next few days?
these next few days?
When are you free?
When are you free?
What's up?
What's up?
I want to treat you to dinner.
I want to treat you to dinner.
My treat—you set it up.
My treat—you set it up.
I'm busy.
I'm busy.
Do you know who contacted me?
Do you know who contacted me?
Zeng Dalun.
Zeng Dalun.
He's doing really well now.
He's doing really well now.
And what's that
And what's that
got to do with me?
got to do with me?
You're close with Cheng Ao, and he's close with Dalun.
You're close with Cheng Ao, and he's close with Dalun.
Help me set up
Help me set up
a dinner with him.
a dinner with him.
If I could work with him,
If I could work with him,
wouldn't our family be better off again?
wouldn't our family be better off again?
You know,
You know,
Zeng Dalun is quite influential now.
Zeng Dalun is quite influential now.
He's very close with the Japanese.
He's very close with the Japanese.
With the current situation
With the current situation
being so tense,
being so tense,
if I could connect with the Japanese through Zeng Dalun,
if I could connect with the Japanese through Zeng Dalun,
wouldn't that be double insurance for our family?
wouldn't that be double insurance for our family?
I understand better than anyone
I understand better than anyone
what it means to adapt to changing circumstances.
what it means to adapt to changing circumstances.
Please leave immediately.
Please leave immediately.
If you don't leave now, I'll call the police.
If you don't leave now, I'll call the police.
You know me well enough.
You know me well enough.
Dalun,
Dalun,
the investigation into Communist supplies
the investigation into Communist supplies
is now in its final stage.
is now in its final stage.
Most of Shanghai's docks have been checked.
Most of Shanghai's docks have been checked.
Now I want to inspect your family's dock.
Now I want to inspect your family's dock.
Our dock?
Our dock?
No way.
No way.
My father isn't pro-Communist.
My father isn't pro-Communist.
He only hates the Japanese.
He only hates the Japanese.
Dalun,
Dalun,
your opium trafficking
your opium trafficking
has been reported to the higher-ups.
has been reported to the higher-ups.
Cooperating with Shen Yiqun this time
Cooperating with Shen Yiqun this time
is your chance to make amends.
is your chance to make amends.
Cooperate?
Cooperate?
Why should I cooperate with Shen Yiqun?
Why should I cooperate with Shen Yiqun?
Who does he think he is?
Who does he think he is?
I've done
I've done
more work for the Revival Society
more work for the Revival Society
than he has lately.
than he has lately.
Dalun,
Dalun,
it's good for young people to have passion.
it's good for young people to have passion.
But politics isn't just about fighting.
But politics isn't just about fighting.
What matters most is brains.
What matters most is brains.
I understand.
I understand.
So according to you,
So according to you,
the deputy director position is basically Shen Yiqun's?
o cargo de subdiretor é basicamente de Shen Yiqun?
Not necessarily.
Não necessariamente.
You might still have a shot.
Talvez ainda tenha uma oportunidade.
What's crucial now is whether we can seize
O que é crucial agora é se podemos aproveitar
that shipment of medicine the Communists are moving out of Shanghai.
aquele carregamento de medicamentos que os comunistas estão a transferir de Xangai.
If you can track down this shipment,
Se puder rastrear esta remessa,
the deputy director position
o cargo de subdiretor
should be yours.
deveria ser seu.
Just bear with it for now.
Tenha apenas paciência por enquanto.
Having you work with Shen Yiqun
Fazendo-o trabalhar com Shen Yiqun
is also what our superiors want.
é também o que os nossos superiores pretendem.
Thank you for your guidance, Director.
Obrigado pela sua orientação, Senhor Diretor.
That's more like it.
É mais ou menos isso.
Remember this,
Lembre-se disso,
the grievance
a queixa
is just a temporary thing.
é apenas algo temporário.
I have high hopes for you.
Tenho grandes esperanças em ti.
Do your best.
Dê o seu melhor.
I'll get to it.
Vou lá chegar.
Go on then.
Então vá em frente.
Cut back on smoking.
Reduza o consumo de cigarros.
Thank you, Director.
Obrigado, Senhor Diretor.
Jin,
Sentimento,
set up a meeting with Mr. Sada for me.
marque uma reunião com o Sr. Sada para mim.
Tell him
Diga-lhe
I need to see him urgently.
Preciso de o ver urgentemente.
Seems Director Liu's words can't be trusted.
Parece que as palavras do Diretor Liu não são fiáveis.
I've never trusted him anyway.
De qualquer forma, nunca confiei nele.
So, what's your plan?
Então, qual é o seu plano?
Take this carton of cigarettes.
Pegue neste maço de cigarros.
Thank you, Young Master.
Obrigado, Jovem Mestre.
Mr. Sada,
Senhor Agora,
we've worked together for a long time—
trabalhamos juntos há muito tempo—
from the Northeast to Shanghai.
do Nordeste para Xangai.
Our business dealings have always gone smoothly.
Os nossos negócios sempre correram bem.
That's true.
Isso é verdade.
Let's drink to our friendship.
Brindemos à nossa amizade.
I have an idea
Eu tenho uma ideia
that not only keeps our business going,
que não só mantém o nosso negócio a funcionar,
but also strengthens my cooperation with the Empire of Japan.
mas também reforça a minha cooperação com o Império do Japão.
Mr. Zeng,
Senhor Zeng,
we've been friends for years.
somos amigos há anos.
Of course I'd welcome deeper cooperation.
É claro que acolheria com agrado uma cooperação mais profunda.
But may I ask,
Mas posso perguntar,
how exactly do you plan
como exatamente planeia
to achieve this?
para conseguir isso?
Shen Yiqun and I
Shen Yiqun e eu
are competing for the deputy director position.
estão a concorrer ao cargo de vice-diretor.
You know what kind of person Shen Yiqun is.
Sabe que tipo de pessoa é Shen Yiqun.
He has always been anti-Japanese.
Sempre foi anti-japonês.
If he becomes the deputy director,
Se ele se tornar o vice-diretor,
it would certainly
certamente seria
be all harm and no good for you.
será apenas mal e nada de bom para si.
But if it's me,
Mas se for eu,
the Kuomintang's door
a porta do Kuomintang
would be your back door.
seria a sua porta das traseiras.
Whatever intelligence you need,
Qualquer informação que necessite,
I can easily provide.
Posso fornecer facilmente.
That's thoughtful of you, Mr. Zeng.
Isso é atencioso da sua parte, Sr. Zeng.
Since you've spoken so frankly,
Já que falou tão francamente,
we will definitely help you win
nós definitivamente ajudaremos a vencer
this position.
esta posição.
I will do my utmost.
Eu farei o meu melhor.
Mr. Gu,
Senhor Gu,
you wanted to see me?
queria ver-me?
The contact I usually work with has been arrested.
O contacto com quem costumo trabalhar foi preso.
The situation is extremely urgent.
A situação é extremamente urgente.
Both the medicine and myself need to be transferred.
Tanto o medicamento como eu precisamos de ser transferidos.
I'll make arrangements.
Vou providenciar.
Be careful.
Tem cuidado.
It's so late.
Está tão tarde.
I just finished a meeting.
Acabei de terminar uma reunião.
The meeting was about
A reunião foi sobre
deploying forces throughout the city to eliminate the Communists.
mobilizando forças por toda a cidade para eliminar os comunistas.
Our principle is to capture them alive if possible,
O nosso princípio é capturá-los vivos, se possível,
but shoot to kill at the slightest resistance.
mas dispare para matar à mínima resistência.
Why are you telling me this?
Por que razão me está a contar isso?
You know this person well, don't you?
Conhece bem essa pessoa, não é?
He's on our elimination list.
Ele está na nossa lista de eliminação.
Once he's captured...
Uma vez capturado...
I don't know if you're familiar
Não sei se está familiarizado
with our torture procedures,
com os nossos procedimentos de tortura,
but no one can withstand them.
mas ninguém lhes pode resistir.
Within 3 days, he will definitely reveal
Dentro de 3 dias, revelará definitivamente
everyone connected to him.
todos ligados a ele.
Aren't you afraid saying this
Não tem medo de dizer isso?
will get you in trouble?
vai colocá-lo em apuros?
I have no choice.
Não tenho escolha.
Here are two steamer tickets.
Aqui estão dois bilhetes de barco a vapor.
Take Siyun and leave Shanghai.
Pegue em Siyun e deixe Xangai.
Go to Chongqing.
Vá para Chongqing.
I'll think about it.
Vou pensar sobre isso.
Cheng Ao,
Cheng Ao,
just think it through.
pense bem nisso.
Make your decision quickly.
Tome a sua decisão rapidamente.
I'm leaving.
Vou embora.
Why such a hurry?
Porquê tanta pressa?
Stay for a drink.
Fique para tomar uma bebida.
Another time—
Outra vez—
once things settle down.
quando as coisas acalmarem.
[Law Firm File]
[Arquivo de Escritório de Advogados]
Why did you suddenly ask me to meet here?
Porque é que de repente me pediu para nos encontrarmos aqui?
When I'm working,
Quando estou a trabalhar,
it's all so fake.
é tudo tão falso.
After so many years in politics,
Depois de tantos anos na política,
meeting different people every day,
conhecendo pessoas diferentes todos os dias,
saying different things to everyone,
dizendo coisas diferentes a cada um,
sometimes I don't even know
às vezes nem sei
if what I'm doing is right or wrong.
se o que estou a fazer é certo ou errado.
It's just so exhausting.
É muito desgastante.
This place is nice.
Este lugar é bonito.
It helps me relax.
Ajuda-me a relaxar.
Have you ever thought
Você já pensou
it's your own ambition
é a sua própria ambição
that's turned you into this?
que te transformou nisso?
My ambition is big, yes.
A minha ambição é grande, sim.
But who doesn't have ambition?
Mas quem não tem ambição?
I've tried to control it—
Eu tentei controlar isso—
but I can't.
mas não consigo.
This is for you.
Isto é para si.
A gift.
Um presente.
I bought a house in Chongqing for you and Cheng Ao.
Comprei uma casa em Chongqing para si e para Cheng Ao.
I've seen the house. It's really nice.
Eu vi a casa. É muito bonita.
You love dogs, right?
Adora cães, certo?
The yard is perfect for that.
O quintal é perfeito para isso.
And don't feel pressured.
E não se sinta pressionado.
Both your names are on the deed.
Os nomes de ambos estão na escritura.
You know what I mean.
Sabe o que quero dizer.
I'm suggesting that you could
Estou a sugerir que poderia
leave Shanghai for a while.
deixe Xangai por uns tempos.
It's so dangerous now, bullets flying every day.
É tão perigoso agora, as balas a voar todos os dias.
What if one day a bullet, bang!
E se um dia uma bala, pimba!
I'm not saying it would hit you.
Não estou a dizer que isso te iria atingir.
But what if it hits Cheng Ao's head?
Mas e se atingir a cabeça de Cheng Ao?
That would be terrible. I'd be devastated.
Isso seria terrível. Eu ficaria devastado.
No one is get shot.
Ninguém leva um tiro.
That's good.
Está bom.
What's good?
O que é bom?
You're so good to Cheng Ao.
És tão bom com Cheng Ao.
Take it.
Pegue.
I can't accept this house.
Não posso aceitar esta casa.
Why not?
Porque não?
Why should I?
Por que razão devo?
Does Cheng Ao know about this?
Cheng Ao sabe disso?
I just went to see him.
Eu só fui vê-lo.
I told him about it.
Contei-lhe sobre isso.
He knows.
Ele sabe.
Alright, I'm not teasing you anymore.
Certo, já não estou a brincar com você.
I didn't buy this house for you two.
Eu não comprei esta casa para os dois.
I just helped you pick it.
Acabei de o ajudar a escolher.
I paid on your behalf.
Eu paguei em seu nome.
Just now in Cheng Ao's office,
Agora mesmo no escritório de Cheng Ao,
he already paid me back.
já me pagou de volta.
And honestly, it's pretty expensive.
E sinceramente, é bastante caro.
I might not even afford it myself.
Talvez nem tenha condições para o pagar.
Cheng Ao treats you
Cheng Ao trata-te
really well.
muito bem.
Now you can accept it, right?
Agora já pode aceitar, certo?
I've had a lock specially made.
Mandei fazer uma fechadura especial.
Here's the key.
Aqui está a chave.
When things settle down someday,
Quando as coisas acalmarem um dia,
I'll come visit you in Chongqing.
Irei visitá-lo em Chongqing.
But promise me—
Mas prometa-me:
save me a room.
guarde um quarto para mim.
Don't turn me away when I come.
Não me rejeite quando eu chegar.
Alright, you go home first.
Tudo bem, vais para casa primeiro.
I'll stay here a bit longer.
Vou ficar aqui mais um bocadinho.
Wait.
Espera.
Be happy!
Seja feliz!
Shen Yiqun!
Shen Yiqun!
Who should not be hurt?
Quem não deve ser ferido?
Cheng Ao.
Cheng Ao.
Young Master,
Jovem Mestre,
we didn't find Cheng Ao's medicine.
não encontramos o remédio de Cheng Ao.
That's impossible.
Isso é impossível.
Search!
Pesquisa!
Yes, sir!
Sim, senhor!
Dad.
Pai.
Zhi,
Zhi,
where did you
onde você
get this deed from?
obter esta escritura de?
I'll count to three.
Vou contar até três.
One—
Um-
Two—
Dois-
I'll tell you.
Eu vou contar-te.
Zhi has confessed that
Zhi confessou que
Zeng Dalun gave her money
Zeng Dalun deu-lhe dinheiro
and a property deed
e uma escritura de propriedade
to put abortion medicine
colocar medicamento para o aborto
into Madam Yanhong's chicken soup.
na canja de galinha da Madame Yanhong.
I see.
Eu vejo.
You may go now.
Pode ir agora.
Dr. Lin,
Dr. Lin,
please have a seat.
Por favor, sente-se.
The other day,
No outro dia,
you were frightened.
estava assustado.
I'm truly sorry about that.
Sinto muito mesmo por isso.
Lately, I've been thinking about
Ultimamente tenho pensado sobre
Cheng Ao
Cheng Ao
and Dalun when they were children.
e Dalun quando eram crianças.
Those two boys
Aqueles dois meninos
always loved running around in the courtyard
sempre adorei correr no pátio
back and forth,
vai e volta,
never sitting still.
nunca estar parado.
A child’s nature shows the adult to come.
A natureza de uma criança mostra o adulto que está para vir.
Dalun has
Dalun tem
been mischievous since childhood.
foi traquina desde a infância.
As for Ao,
As for Ao,
he has always been very steady.
ele sempre foi muito estável.
Dr. Lin,
Dr. Lin,
can you forgive me?
pode perdoar-me?
Here's a small gift from me.
Aqui está um pequeno presente meu.
Please don't refuse it.
Por favor, não recuse.
Take it.
Pegue.
It's from Father.
É do Pai.
Dad,
Pai,
I did it,
Eu fiz isso,
but it was to protect you.
mas era para o proteger.
Dad,
Pai,
have you seen Cheng Ao?
já viu o Cheng Ao?
Do you want him dead too?
Quer que ele morra também?
Dad,
Pai,
how could I?
como poderia?
You and Cheng Ao are the closest people to me.
Tu e o Cheng Ao são as pessoas mais próximas de mim.
Ao has a shipment of goods.
Ao tem uma remessa de mercadorias.
If you give me that shipment,
Se me der essa remessa,
I will get promoted.
Eu serei promovido.
By then, what's mine
Até lá, o que é meu?
will be yours and Cheng Ao's too.
será seu e de Cheng Ao também.
Go!
Ir!
I'll say this one last time.
Direi isso uma última vez.
No dealings with the Japanese.
Sem negociação com os japoneses.
The medicines and equipment are all packed.
Os medicamentos e equipamentos estão todos embalados.
Ready to depart anytime.
Pronto para partir a qualquer momento.
Mr. Cheng,
Senhor Cheng,
I hope one day
Espero que um dia
you will join us.
irá juntar-se a nós.
Those with determination
Aqueles com determinação
will eventually find their path
eventualmente encontrarão o seu caminho
toward the right goal.
em direção ao objetivo certo.
Take care once you leave Shanghai.
Tenha cuidado ao sair de Xangai.
Mr. Cheng,
Senhor Cheng,
farewell.
adeus.
Cheng Ao,
Cheng Ao,
if there were more people like Mr. Gu,
se houvesse mais pessoas como o Sr. Gu,
our country would have hope, wouldn't it?
o nosso país teria esperança, não é?
I believe so.
Acredito que sim.
We must strive to be like him.
Devemos esforçar-nos para ser como ele.
On August 13th, 1937,
A 13 de agosto de 1937,
the Battle of Shanghai broke out.
eclodiu a Batalha de Xangai.
Sinan Maternity Hospital
Hospital Maternidade Sinan
has been used during the war,
foi utilizado durante a guerra,
receiving injured soldiers and refugees.
recebendo soldados feridos e refugiados.
[Our Forces Strike Back, Enemy Suffers Heavy Losses'
[As nossas forças contra-atacam, o inimigo sofre pesadas perdas'
[Shanghai Suburbs, August 1937]
[Subúrbios de Xangai, agosto de 1937]
To protect our homeland,
Para proteger a nossa pátria,
to protect our families—
para proteger as nossas famílias—
today
hoje
we march to the front.
marchamos para a frente.
Maybe today we fight,
Talvez hoje lutemos,
and tomorrow we never come back!
e amanhã nunca mais voltamos!
But as soldiers,
Mas, como soldados,
as sons of China,
como filhos da China,
we do not fear death.
não tememos a morte.
Trained for 1,000 days,
Treinado durante 1.000 dias,
used in one moment—
usado num momento—
now
agora
it's our turn to fight!
é a nossa vez de lutar!
Left face!
Rosto esquerdo!
Quick march!
Marcha rápida!
Director, more wounded are coming in.
Senhor Diretor, mais feridos estão a chegar.
What do we do?
O que fazemos?
Put them in the main ward.
Coloque-os na ala principal.
Clean their wounds, disinfect and bandage them.
Limpe os seus ferimentos, desinfete-os e faça curativos.
Gather those who need surgery.
Reúna aqueles que precisam de cirurgia.
I'll come over as soon as I finish here.
Irei lá assim que terminar aqui.
Understood.
Compreendido.
I'm really smart, you know.
Eu sou muito inteligente, sabias?
Do you know what these mirrors
Sabe o que são estes espelhos?
are for?
são para?
In a couple of days,
Em alguns dias,
when Japanese planes come,
quando chegam os aviões japoneses,
we'll place these mirrors
vamos colocar estes espelhos
at the most important National Army positions—
nas posições mais importantes do Exército Nacional —
grain depots,
depósitos de grãos,
command posts,
postos de comando,
and arsenals.
e arsenais.
When these mirrors reflect light,
Quando estes espelhos refletem a luz,
the Japanese planes
os aviões japoneses
will hit their targets with precision.
atingirão os seus alvos com precisão.
This glass is quite sturdy.
Este vidro é bastante resistente.
Go break it.
Vá parti-lo.
Okay.
Ok.
Nobody move!
Ninguém se mexa!
Get down!
Abaixe-se!
Stop right there!
Pare mesmo aí!
Dad,
Pai,
I'm negotiating with the Japanese,
Estou a negociar com os japoneses,
trying for a ceasefire.
tentando um cessar-fogo.
They've agreed.
Eles concordaram.
As long as the National Army
Enquanto o Exército Nacional
withdraws from Shanghai,
retira-se de Xangai,
they promised to treat our people well.
prometeram tratar bem o nosso povo.